Finding Aid for Shaw Family (Adrian, Mich.) papers, 1840-1938
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Shaw Family (Adrian, Mich.) papers 1840-1938, 1860-1890
Shaw family.
1 linear feet
8682 Aa 2
Family of Brackley Shaw of Adrian, Michigan, Republican state representative from Lenawee County, Michigan, 1869-1870, later state senator, 1881-1884. The collection consists of personal correspondence of Shaw, his son Horatio W., and his brother Horatio W. Shaw.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Roger Palpant (donor no. 4004 ) and came to the library in 1963.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Brackley Shaw was a Republican member of the Michigan Legislature (1869-1870) and of the Michigan Senate (1881-1884). Horatio W. Shaw was a Presbyterian minister and missionary to India. Brackley Shaw's son, also Horatio W. Shaw, was an artist.
The Shaw family collection consists of letters to and from several members of the Shaw family of Lenawee County during the period 1840-1938, with the bulk falling in the years roughly 1860-1890. Family members represented include Horatio Shaw (1822-1910), a Presbyterian missionary and clergyman; his brother, Brackley Shaw (b. 1818), member of the Michigan Legislature (1869-70; 1881-84); and Brackley's son, Horatio W. Shaw (1847-1918), Michigan artist. The letters have been described by chronological time period.
1845-1848: Letters from Horatio Shaw to Brackley Shaw
1850-1859: Largely family correspondence, including some letters home (1855, 1857) from Reverend and Mrs. Horatio Shaw from their missionary station in Allahabad, India.
1860-1865: Correspondence includes a few items pertaining to the Civil War, most of which does not relate to Michigan.
1866-1870: A great deal of political correspondence is included in these years, particularly during 1869, when Brackley Shaw served as a Republican member of the state House of Representatives from Lenawee County. There are letters from Shaw to his wife describing events in Lansing, and correspondence with various persons on such subjects as railroads, prisons and other state institutions, and dentistry regulation. There is also a letter of H. E. Baker (Detroit Advertiser and Tribune) to Brackley Shaw, dated December 25, 1668, with comments on the character of Senator Zachariah Chandler.
1871-1879: Mostly family correspondence, including letters written from White Cloud, Kansas, with descriptions of conditions there in the late 1860's and early 1870's.
1880-1890: Considerable political correspondence during Brackley Shaw's two terms as Republican member of the state senate (1880-1884). Topics covered include: homeopathic medicines, temperance and prohibition, Republican Party politics, prisons and reformatories, protection for corporate minority stockholders, and a great deal of correspondence pertaining to the election of a United States Senator in the spring of 1983. There is a large collection of letters from Shaw to his wife describing his senatorial activities. Also included are letters, 1881, 1383, 1884, from various Philadelphia artists to Horatio Shaw, the painter, and letters, 1881-92, from H. Shaw (signed "Pat") to his wife Susie. Some letters contain references to well-known American painters of the time, including comments on Shaw's style and abilities as an artist
1891-1936: family correspondence.
Subjects:
Adrian (Mich.); Dentistry--Michigan.; Homeopathy--Michigan.; Kansas.; Lenawee County (Mich.); Michigan. Legislature (25th: 1869-1870); Michigan. Legislature (31st: 1881-1882); Michigan. Legislature (32nd: 1883); Michigan--Politics and government--1866-1876.; Michigan--Politics and government--1877-1898.; Missionaries.; Presbyterian Church--Michigan.; Prisons--Michigan.; Prohibition--Michigan.; Railroads--Michigan.; Reformatories--Michigan.; Republican Party (Mich.); Temperance--Michigan.; United States. Army. Indiana Infantry Regiment, 29th (1861-1865); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Begole, Josiah Williams, 1815-1896.; Chandler, Zachariah, 1813-1879.; Eakins, Thomas, 1844-1916.; Palmer, Thomas Witherell, 1830-1913.; Whistler, James McNeill, 1834-1903.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Women--Michigan--Adrian.
Contributors:
Shaw, Brackley, b. 1818.; Baldwin, Henry P. (Henry Porter), 1814-1892.; Ferry, Thomas White, 1827-1896.; Hall, Emma Amelia, 1837-1884.; Rynd, Charles, 1836-1884.; Shaw, Horatio Watson, 1822-1910.; Shaw, Horatio Watson, 1847-1918.; Stephens, Frank, 1859-1935.
- Correspondence
  - Undated 1840s-1859 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous and undated (Box 1)
  - Letters from Horatio W. Shaw to his brother Brackley Shaw 1845-1848 (Box 1)
  - 1840s (Box 1)
  - 1850-1859 (Box 1)
  - 1861-1862 (Box 1)
  - 1863 (Box 1)
  - 1864 (Box 1)
  - 1865 (Box 1)
  - 1866 (Box 1)
  - 1867 (Box 1)
  - 1868 (Box 1)
  - 1869 (Box 1)
  - 1870 (Box 1)
  - 1871 (Box 1)
  - 1872 (Box 1)
  - 1873 (Box 1)
  - 1874 (Box 1)
  - 1875-1876 (Box 1)
  - 1877-1879 (Box 1)
  - January-October 1880 (Box 1)
  - November-December 1880 (Box 1)
  - January-February 1881 (Box 1)
  - March 1881 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1881 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1881 (Box 1)
  - January-February 1882 (Box 1)
  - March-October 1882 (Box 1)
  - November-December 1882 (Box 1)
  - January 1-15, 1883 (Box 1)
  - January 16-31, 1883 (Box 1)
  - February 1883 (Box 1)
  - March 1883 (Box 1)
  - April 1883 (Box 1)
  - May, 1883 (Box 1)
  - June-December 1883 (Box 1)
  - 1884 (Box 1)
  - 1885 (Box 1)
  - 1886-1890 (Box 1)
  - 1891-1900 (Box 1)
  - 1901-1911 (Box 1)
  - 1935-1938 (Box 1)
Selective Index to Correspondents and Topics
Baldwin, Henry Porter, 1814-1892.
Letter, April 7, 1883, of Henry P. Baldwin, to Brackley Shaw requesting negative vote on the Bolger Bill to regulate convict labor.
Begole, Josiah Williams, 1815-1896.
Letter, December 30, 1882, from Emma Amelia Hall to Brackley Shaw, with extensive comments on Governor Josiah Williams Begole.
Chandler, Zachariah, 1813-1879.
Letter, December 28, 1868, of H.E. Baker to Brackley Shaw, containing extensive comments on the character and habits of United States Senator Zach Chandler.
Eakins, Thomas, 1844-1916.
Letters, November 1881-January 1882, containing references to the artist Thomas Eakins.
Ferry, Thomas White, 1827-1896.
Letter, October 31, 1882, from Senator Thomas W. Ferry to Brackley Shaw, with reference to election campaign of the fall of 1882; also, considerable correspondence, January-March, 1883, pertaining to his unsuccessful bid for re-election to the U.S. Senate.
Hall, Emma Amelia, 1837-1884.
Letters, December 30, 1882, and January 1, 1883, from Emma Hall to Brackley Shaw, concerning Michigan Reform School for Girls at Adrian.
Palmer, Thomas Witherell, 1830-1913.
Considerable information pertaining to the United States senatorial election of 1883, contained in the correspondence of Brackley Shaw. This contest eventually resulted in the election of Thomas W. Palmer to the seat formerly held by Thomas W. Ferry.
Rynd, Charles, 1836-1884.
Letter, May 21, 1883, from Charles Rynd to Brackley Shaw requesting favorable note on measure to give minority representation to stockholders on corporate boards of directors.
Shaw, Horatio Watson, 1822-1910
Civil War letters of Horatio W. Shaw, chaplain in the 29th Indiana Infantry.
Stephens, Frank, 1859-1935.
Letters, January 28, 1884; February 20, 1884; and March 2, 1888, from sculptor (George "Kid") Frank Stephens to Horatio W. Shaw and his wife.
Whistler, James Abbott McNeil, 1834-1903.
Letter, November 13, 1881, of Horatio Shaw containing reference to the artist, James Abbott McNeil Whistler.